<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>Fryzek Concepts</title><atom:link href="https://fryzekconcepts.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><link>https://fryzekconcepts.com</link><description>Lucas is a developer working on cool things</description><lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2023 15:38:08 -0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Generating Video</title><link>https://fryzekconcepts.com/notes/generating-video.html</link><description>One thing I’m very interested in is computer graphics. This could be complex 3D graphics or simple 2D graphics. The idea of getting a computer to display visual data fascinates me. One fundamental part of showing visual data is interfacing with a computer monitor. This can be accomplished by generating a video signal that the monitor understands. Below I have written instructions on how an FPGA can be used to generate a video signal. I have specifically worked with the iCEBreaker FPGA but the...</description><pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2020 04:00:00 -0000</pubDate><guid>https://fryzekconcepts.com/notes/generating-video.html</guid></item><item><title>N64Brew GameJam 2021</title><link>https://fryzekconcepts.com/notes/n64brew-gamejam-2021.html</link><description>So this year myself and two others decided to participate together in the N64Brew homebrew GameJam where we were supposed to build a homebrew game that would run on a real Nintendo 64. The game jam took place from October 8th until December 8th and was the second GameJam in N64Brew history. Unfortunately we never ended up finishing the game but we did build a really cool tech demo. Our project was called Bug Game and if you want to check it out you can find it here. To play the game   a...</description><pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 05:00:00 -0000</pubDate><guid>https://fryzekconcepts.com/notes/n64brew-gamejam-2021.html</guid></item><item><title>Rasterizing Triangles</title><link>https://fryzekconcepts.com/notes/rasterizing-triangles.html</link><description>Lately I’ve been trying to implement a software renderer following the algorithm described by Juan Pineda in A Parallel Algorithm for Polygon Rasterization. For those unfamiliar with the paper it describes an algorithm to rasterize triangles that has an extremely nice quality that you simply need to preform a few additions per pixel to see if the next pixel is inside the triangle. It achieves this quality by defining an edge function that has the following property:This property is  nice  a...</description><pubDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2022 04:00:00 -0000</pubDate><guid>https://fryzekconcepts.com/notes/rasterizing-triangles.html</guid></item><item><title>Baremetal RISC-V</title><link>https://fryzekconcepts.com/notes/baremetal-risc-v.html</link><description>After re-watching suckerpinch’s Reverse Emulation video I got inspired to try and replicate what he did but instead do it on an N64. Now my idea here is not to preform reverse emulation on the N64 itself but instead to use the SBC as a cheap way to make a dev focused flash cart. Seeing that sukerpinch was able to meet the timings of the NES bus made me think it might be possible to meet the N64 bus timings taking an approach similar to his.Why RISC-V Baremetal? - The answer here is more    I...</description><pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2022 04:00:00 -0000</pubDate><guid>https://fryzekconcepts.com/notes/baremetal-risc-v.html</guid></item><item><title>Digital Garden</title><link>https://fryzekconcepts.com/notes/digital_garden.html</link><description>After reading Maggie Appleton page on digital gardens I was inspired to convert my own website into a digital garden.I have many half baked ideas that I seem to be able to finish. Some of them get to a published state like  and  but many of them never make it to the published state. The idea of digital garden seems very appealing to me as it encourages you to post on a topic even if you haven’t made it publishable yet.How this site works - I wanted a bit of challenge when putting together...</description><pubDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2022 04:00:00 -0000</pubDate><guid>https://fryzekconcepts.com/notes/digital_garden.html</guid></item><item><title>2022 Graphics Team Contributions at Igalia</title><link>https://fryzekconcepts.com/notes/2022_igalia_graphics_team.html</link><description>This year I started a new job working with Igalia’s Graphics Team. For those of you who don’t know Igalia they are a worker-owned employee-run cooperative model consultancy focused on open source software.As a new member of the team I thought it would be a great idea to summarize the incredible amount of work the team completed in 2022. If you’re interested keep reading!Vulkan 1.2 Conformance on RPi 4 - One of the big milestones for the team in 2022 was achieving Vulkan 1.2 conformance...</description><pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2023 05:00:00 -0000</pubDate><guid>https://fryzekconcepts.com/notes/2022_igalia_graphics_team.html</guid></item></channel></rss>